<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King. The kings Maiestie intending to follovv the godly and honourable statutes and ordinances of houshold of his most noble progenitors ...</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1618-11-10</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22167</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8580</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100769</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836598</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836598</idno>
            <idno type="VID">882</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22167)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 882)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1686:38)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King. The kings Maiestie intending to follovv the godly and honourable statutes and ordinances of houshold of his most noble progenitors ...</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1618-11-10</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Bonham Norton,and Iohn Bill, deputie printers for the Kings most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. M.DC.XVIII. [1618]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sending away hangers-on at the Court.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: Whitehall, the tenth day of Nouember, in the sixteenth yeere of our reigne ..</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rogues and vagabonds --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:882:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
            <head>¶ By the King.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Kings Maieſtie intending to follow the</hi> godly and honourable Statutes and Ordinances of Houſhold of his moſt Noble Progenitors, ſtraitly chargeth and commandeth, that all Vagabonds and Maſterleſſe folke, boyes and girles, and other idle perſons which haue vſed to hang on, haunt, and follow the Court, ſhall depart from thence within foure and twentie houres af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this Proclamation made, vpon paine of his Maieſties grieuous diſpleaſure, and ſuch further paines, as in the ſaid Statutes and Ordinances be limitted and appoited. And further, that no Artificer, Laundrer or Laundreſſe, other then ſuch as ſhall bee ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally licenſed, ſhall follow the Court: And they that ſhall be ſo admitted, to haue with them no maner of young children, or other ſeruants, either of men or women kinde, then ſhall be ſpecially limitted and enrolled. And moreouer, that no Officer of the Houſhold, nor any other perſon or perſons lodged within his Maieſties moſt Honourable Houſe, doe ſuffer any Vagabonds, Maſterleſſe folkes, boyes or other idle perſons whatſoeuer, to reſort into their Chambers, and Offices at any time, vpon paine of impriſonment in the Marſhalſeas, and further puniſhment at his Maieſties will and pleaſure. Alſo that all Lords and others that haue lodging in the Houſe, ſhall foorthwith ſend the names of their ſeruants to the Knight Marſhall to be Regiſtred; and if they ſhall put any of them away for miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanour, to ſend him to the Marſhall, that he may be diſcharged accordingly. Further, that no chamber-keeper preſume to keepe boyes, or ſcrapers of trenchers, other then ſuch as ſhall be thought meet and conuenient to be allowed. And laſtly, his Maieſtie ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chargeth and commandeth his Knight Marſhall, and all ſuch Officers and Miniſters as be attendant about the Court vnder him and euery of them, to doe their vttermoſt and beſt endeauour from time to ſee his Maieſties commandement, aboue ſpecified, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially obſerued, obeyed and kept, as they will auoide his Maieſties grieuous diſpleaſure, and anſwere to the contrary at their perils.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at Whitehall, <date>the tenth day of Nouember, in the ſixteenth yeere of Our Reigne of England, France, and Ireland, and of Scotland the two and fiftieth.</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Bonham Norton, and Iohn Bill, deputie Printers for the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>ANNO. M.DC.XVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
